What does it mean to you to return to Nir Oz?
It took me some time to have the guts to come back
and visit Kibbutz Nir Oz.
People from overseas always ask me how...
how it is to go back, how it feels,
what is going on in your house.
And it's really very hard to put into words.
I wish you could all be here, because
being here makes the information we know sink in
and creates some kind of feeling
that only those who know Nir Oz
can understand Nir Oz.
But thanks to photography,
we can bring it as close to you as we can,
so you can not only see,
but maybe feel through the pictures,
the silence of the dead,
the beauty of the vegetation,
the sounds of the birds in the sky,
and the memory of so many people who
were hoping to live in peace,
and in good relations with their neighbors
10 minutes away from here.
People who worked hard,
who lived modest lives, who were productive,
who were loving and happy.
And yet, through all this,
even with 95% of the houses in this place burned,
we see some hope growing.
We will never forget.
We will never stop hurting.
But in order to continue living,
we have to cling to hope and to the return
of the people of Nir Oz,
like my uncle and my aunt.
We shall overcome, and light shall overcome the shadows.
The shadows remain,
and you can probably see them in the pictures,
but there is no shadow without light.
And...
we concentrate on the light.
I want to say something.
I encourage every German citizen who wants to understand
what truly happened
to come and visit Israel.
Please ask questions, please find out and seek the truth,
and then judge for yourself.
What do you feel? What do you think?
And most importantly,
what do you think should happen in the future?
How can we strengthen Israel?
How can we secure the safety of the people of Israel,
who deserve to be in their land,
but at the same time
contribute to a better neighborhood
and to rebuilding the region?
What did you experience on October 7?
I live in a village about 30 minutes away.
I woke up to calls from my daughter, who said, "Mom,
Mom, I hear terrible sounds."
And within a minute, we had a siren.
I ran with the whole family into the safe room,
where we don't have any reception.
We waited the amount of time we always have to wait,
and we're very used to it,
and came out. Then it sounded like hell.
And I immediately called my cousin, who was there—
here with her...
two daughters. I spoke to her.
She was absolutely terrified.
We decided we would talk later,
and I immediately called my aunt,
who was already whispering and said,
"I can hear Arabic. I can hear calls against us.
I hear a terrible sound." And I told her,
"So why are you talking to me?
Stay in the safe room." And she said,
"They're here, they're here."
And I told her, "Please,
please, aunty,
hang up. I will call my parents.
I will tell them not to call you."
And we didn't for many hours,
because we had no clue what was going on,
but we wanted to be as safe as we could, to protect them.
And later...
later, we saw the terrible videos,
the propaganda clips that the terrorists released,
and we actually realized
it was my aunt on the golf cart,
and other people we knew.
Later, we saw
a picture of my uncle being carried by two jihadists,
and we knew life would never be the same.
What was your first impression
when you came back to Nir Oz?
It's really difficult for me to speak about time.
I'm not sure how many months had passed. I think it was...
maybe...
four...
three or four months.
And the first time I came here,
my heart was beating so fast.
And what struck me was the fact that
the birds were singing and everything was so green,
but the smell was like hell,
because for months and months and months,
we could still smell the fire in the air,
and that was devastating.
And the sense of smell actually
overwhelmed all the other senses,
and it was just shocking. It was absolutely shocking.
And it reminded me of the moral hell we are in,
where we want to believe in peace,
and we want to believe in coexistence.
This is what I did all my life,
lecturing on multiculturalism, diversity, coexistence.
And now I need to deal with this piece of history,
and I need to refine my thoughts,
and I need to overcome my feelings,
and I need to connect to the DNA
of my humanistic view of the world.
It's not easy. It's a challenge, but we are on the way.
What will life here be like in a couple of months or years?
When my uncle was released,
when he was taken in the helicopter,
he already said, "I know Nir Oz has been burned,
but I shall come and rebuild Nir Oz."
And that's what he is doing, along with other good people
who managed and chose to come back,
and others who will join them.
And life takes over. We will never forget,
but we shall continue living.
And what you see now is a historical record:
the burned houses, the burned remains,
the death you see will be replaced by new houses, bigger,
better education, resilience,
lots of kids running, and again,
life will return with the memory of what happened,
with caution in what we say and how we act,
but with a lot of hope.
Terrorism will not win.
Terrorism is a terrible philosophy.
I'm not sure we will be able
to cut its roots,
but we will be able to work on better education
for years and years to come.
It will take a very long time,
but we must believe that the right education will grow
a different generation
that chooses life over revenge and death.
And they will not win.
They might burn, but we rebuild.
They might break, but we fix.
Because we are stronger than this destruction.
We are stronger than this atrocity.
We are the power of humanity.
How do you feel about the support from Europe
and all the other countries that have abandoned Israel?
I am very grateful for countries like Germany
that were really very...
supportive from the very beginning
and showed solidarity.
But there is something that I have to admit.
As much as I want things to be prettier and
more beautiful, they're not always like that.
And...
I wish the world leaders
and the European leaders had pushed earlier.
We're very hopeful that this is coming to an end,
but this should have happened in November.
We lost so many lives that we could have saved.
We lost so many people,
and the ripples of pain are growing and growing
and growing across the whole state.
It's not only our families,
it's our communities and our cities and villages.
And it's not only Israel,
because the world is going through a catastrophe,
a humanitarian... a humanitarian crisis.
So why be so late? Why not act
when it's happening?
How could anyone let this continue for such a long time?
I have no answers.
But I am grateful for every hug
and every effort that was made,
sometimes without us seeing or knowing.
I still believe that things were done,
or were at least approached or started,
because I still, whatever happens,
believe in humanity.